<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-04-16T23:06:06+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">同志社大学社会学研究科　陳凌雲</title><subtitle>普段研究している内容を発信します。</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Social Work Practice with Communities - Intervention, Termination, and Evaluation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/social%20work%20practice/2023/04/16/Social-work-practice-with-community.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Social Work Practice with Communities - Intervention, Termination, and Evaluation" /><published>2023-04-16T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2023-04-16T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/social%20work%20practice/2023/04/16/Social%20work%20practice%20with%20community</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/social%20work%20practice/2023/04/16/Social-work-practice-with-community.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="書籍">書籍</h1>
<p>Birkenmaier, J., &amp; Berg-Weger, M. (2020). <em>The practice of generalist social work</em>. Routledge.P496-527</p>

<h1 id="begin">Begin</h1>

<p>LIKE SOCIAL WORK PRACTICE WITH INDIVIDUALS, FAMILIES, AND GROUPS, 
the middle and ending phases of work with communities are intervention ,termination, evaluation, and follow-up. As noted in Chapter 10, community practice is a broad term that includes grassroots community organizing, community development, human service program development, planning and coordination, and advocacy (Weil, Gamble, &amp; Ohmer, 2013). There are many types of community interventions, all of which are based on the data gathered and process used for community assessment. The aim of many community practice interventions is to build community capacity and shape institutional arrangements that meet the needs of community members.</p>

<p>In this chapter, we begin with a discussion of theoretical traditions and practice models that can help guide social work intervention with communities. Our focus is on the most recognized models of community intervention, as well as the ways in which they can be mixed in practice. After providing an overview of social work interventions with communities, the chapter continues with a look at the termination, evaluation, and follow-up processes.</p>

<h1 id="theoretical-traditions-and-models-for-community-intervention">Theoretical traditions and models for community intervention</h1>

<p>As we discussed in Chapter 10, conceptual and theoretical traditions in social work provide a lens through which to understand and analyze communities. For example, you can apply the strengths approach to communities by identifying assets and resources of individuals, groups, and institutions in that community. You can achieve the empowerment approach by helping community members realize their capacity to build on the community’s strengths (Netting et al., 2017).</p>

<p>Community practice models, which are primarily based in the concepts and language of systems, ecological, power, change, and politics theories, guide community interventions (Netting et al., 2017). As Exhibit 11.1 notes, systems theory helps to demonstrate that planned community change reverberates throughout a community and affects units within and outside of a community. Therefore, when you choose a community intervention, you should consider the possibility that community change may affect more people than you intend.</p>

<p>Ecological theory’s focus on competition for limited resources, which can affect the relationships among different parts of a community or between communities, informs community interventions. Theoretical traditions that focus on power, change, and politics emphasize the ways in which external forces influence local communities and the ways in which some members of a community possess social or political power while other members do not. Social workers in community practice can help members of a community critically examine both external and internal power and the influence of the various types of power. Without examining power dynamics, community members cannot have honest and open discussions about what is best for the community as a whole, and how to establish priorities for their community’s future.</p>

<h3 id="exhibit-111-understanding-community-practice-theoretical-contributions">Exhibit 11.1 Understanding Community Practice: Theoretical Contributions</h3>
<p>| Theoretical                 | Contributions to understanding community practice                                                                               |
| ————————— | ——————————————————————————————————————————- |
| Social systems              | Reveals that changes in one community unit impact other units indicates that changes in subunits influence the larger community |
|                             | Allows comparisons of the functioning of different communities                                                                  |
| Ecological                  | Sheds light on relationships among community units                                                                              |
|                             | Recognizes that community groups compete for limited resources                                                                  |
|                             | Recognizes that groups without power must adapt to community norms                                                              |
|                             | Acknowledges the interconnections and mutual shaping of physical and social structures                                          |
| Power, Change, and politics | Reveals the influence of external sources of resources on communities                                                           |
|                             | Views the community as divided into “haves” and “have-nots”                                                                     |
|                             | Focuses heavily on “isms” such as racism                                                                                        |
|                             | Acknowledges the role of power in all interpersonal transactions                                                                |
Source: Netting, Kettner, McMurtry, &amp; Thomas, 2017</p>

<p>As highlighted in Chapter 10, data from the community-assessment process provides the basis for community change efforts, which often use a variety of approaches. The models most common in the literature are Rothman’s (2008) three models of community practice: planning/policy, community capacity development, and social advocacy. These three models have the goal of improving social, economic, and/or environmental well-being and share several common elements, including the following:</p>

<p>• the formulation of a change goal,</p>

<p>• roles for staff,</p>

<p>• leaders and members,</p>

<p>• a process for selecting issues to work on,</p>

<p>• a target of the change effort,</p>

<p>• assessment of resources needed to produce change, and</p>

<p>• an understanding of the role of organizations in the change process.</p>

<h2 id="the-planningpolicy-model">the planning/policy Model</h2>

<p>The planning/policy model of community intervention focuses on data and logic to achieve community change, using experts to assist in the process of studying problems and applying rational planning techniques. Social workers using social planning consider political realities and the usefulness of advocacy in the intervention process, but the primary emphasis is on rational planning.</p>

<p>The planning/policy model can be implemented in a range of practice situations. Social workers engage in social planning when they participate in efforts to envision, develop, coordinate, deliver, and improve human services. Planning is needed for all types of human services (i.e., child welfare, health, aging) and topics (i.e., gang violence, neighborhood development), and in all types of host organizations, including local, state, or federal governments, faith-based organizations, and community councils (Sager &amp; Weil, 2013). As one example, social workers prioritize data when they are involved in comprehensive planning, such as working with city officials to create a plan for homeless shelters or juvenile justice facilities in the community. In these situations, data from local nonprofit organizations, local and state governments, and the U.S. Census Bureau can be of great use in shaping decisions.</p>

<h2 id="the-community-capacity-development-model">The Community Capacity development Model</h2>

<p>The community capacity development model focuses on fostering the community’s ability to accomplish change by building relationships and skills that help solve local problems in a cooperative manner. Participant consensus is the optimal decision-making process for this model. This model emphasizes building competency of community members, groups, and the community as a whole through self-help and local problem-solving. Building community capacity often focuses on empowerment of members, solidarity among members, participation in civic action within a democratic process, and the development of leadership from the community. For example, neighborhood associations may work to educate themselves on ways to address a trash dumping problem. The work of the U.S. Peace Corps, in which international volunteers work with local communities to create a project or increase capacity in an ongoing community effort, is another example of the community capacity development model.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For another example of the community capacity development model, we return to Taylor and Ben, the social workers who are planning a barbeque for youth from a school and older adults from a nearby senior center. Taylor spoke ahead of time with two students who had excellent communication skills and asked them to help barbeque and serve food. Ben similarly lined up two senior center leaders to help. This planning seemed to smooth the initial moments of the “meet-and-greet” and gave the two age groups a chance to begin getting to know one another. Soon after people began to finish their meals, Taylor and Ben started the discussion by explaining how “brainstorming” worked and then asking everyone to share ideas for small enterprises that would help build new skills for the youth while also meeting needs in the larger community.</p>

  <p>A number of people shared ideas for small businesses that seemed feasible. One of the older adults said that he would love to have salads and vegetables with the senior center congregate meals that many participants brought as side dishes to accompany the barbeque. While he contributed the idea as a complement to the cooks, one of the students said that he would grow vegetables for the senior center if he knew anything about gardening. Another student said she would be happy to help cook vegetables if she knew anything about cooking. These comments had the group laughing but also led to a sharing of stories from the older adults about learning how to garden and cook as children.</p>

  <p>By the end of the meet-and-greet, an idea for a small community garden had begun to form. Many of the youth seemed interested in learning how to grow vegetables for older adults to add to their congregate meals, and in being able to sell the leftover vegetables to neighbors for a reasonable price. Several older adults offered to help plan the community garden and teach the youth how to cultivate and harvest vegetables. Others had little interest in working outside during the summer heat but said they would be happy to teach students how to prepare and cook vegetable dishes. One of the youths suggested creating a digital cookbook featuring vegetables from the community garden and selling e-copies to earn money to help sustain the garden. The group agreed to meet again the following week to develop a list of what each person could do to contribute to the community gardening effort. Taylor and Ben had successfully used a community capacity development model to form a collaborative intergenerational team to improve the neighborhood.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="the-social-advocacy-model">the social advocacy Model</h2>

<p>The social advocacy model is based in theoretical traditions that focus on conflict, power dependency, and resource mobilization. This model is both process and task-oriented and focuses on shifting power relationships and redistributing resources to facilitate change in community structures or institutions to resolve problems affecting many residents. Through this model, community members often experience empowerment when they feel a sense of achievement in helping to influence decisions and policies that affect the entire community.</p>

<p>A helpful example of the social advocacy model is the work of Greenpeace. To seek solutions to environmental dilemmas, such as climate change, Greenpeace nonviolently confronts decision-makers and those who may influence decision-makers. The goal of their work is to promote public dialog about environmental issues and to advocate for policies that protect the earth.</p>

<p>As listed in Quick Guide 32, there are a wide variety of social advocacy activities, including, but not limited to, protesting, striking, walking on picket lines, and testifying (Rothman, 2008; Weil &amp; Gamble, 2009).</p>

<h2 id="applying-community-practice-models-to-a-case-example">Applying Community Practice Models to a Case example</h2>

<h3 id="activities-to-promote-social-change">Activities to Promote Social Change</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Conduct petition drives</li>
  <li>==Conduct public hearings==</li>
  <li>==Develop relationships with decision-makers==</li>
  <li>File complaints</li>
  <li>Lobby decision-makers</li>
  <li>Organize boycotts</li>
  <li>Organize public demonstrations</li>
  <li>Organize strikes</li>
  <li>==Provide testimony==</li>
  <li>Recruit and develop leaders</li>
  <li>Register voters</li>
  <li>Use legal action</li>
  <li>==Use media==</li>
  <li>==Write letters to legislators and/or the media==
Sources: Bobo, Kendall, &amp; Max, 2010; University of Kansas Work Group for Community Health and Development, 2018</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="applying-community-practice-models-to-the-brickville-redevelopment-example">Applying Community Practice Models to the Brickville Redevelopment Example</h3>

<p>The Brickville community is in a quandary. Although the community needs redevelopment, the current proposal to completely overhaul the physical structures in the community, including razing some buildings, has stirred major controversy among current community residents, neighborhood social service providers, and sympathetic outsiders. The community has had little input into the plan, and some residents fear that they would no longer be able to afford to live in the neighborhood after the redevelopment. For example, after similar redevelopment efforts in other parts of the city, both rents and property taxes have increased, leading to long-term residents needing to move to more affordable neighborhoods. Other people do not like the plan itself, believing that the planned changes in community real estate will change the look and character of the area. Some residents think that the community will benefit from redevelopment despite the possible negative effects. Still others do not trust the developer who has proposed the redevelopment. Over the past half-century, real estate developers have made several half-hearted efforts to redevelop the residential and commercial parts of the community, with little success. However, several real estate developers are now working to redevelop different areas of the community, and all are requesting public funding in addition to applying for loans from area banks for their development efforts. While some developers are working with current residents, most have not asked community groups or local political leaders for their input or feedback on the redevelopment plans.</p>

<p><strong>The Planning/Policy Model</strong>: Using the planning/policy model, the community group or local political leader would request that city planners generate data or use previously existing data to create a redevelopment plan for the community to which all developers would have to adhere.</p>

<p><strong>The Community Capacity Development Model</strong>: using the community capacity development model, one or more community groups from the affected area would begin a process of developing their ability to create a comprehensive community redevelopment plan that they could present to real estate developers and/or city officials.</p>

<p><strong>The Social Advocacy Model</strong>: using the social advocacy model, one or more leaders from the affected area would organize community residents and groups to communicate with specific decision-makers, and sometimes bring pressure to bear as needed, to affect outcomes of interest such as zoning ordinances, public funding, and the availability and structure of tax breaks for redevelopers. advocacy efforts including messaging workshops, sign-making parties for public protests, and strategic timing and locations for community outreach and educational events would likely be involved using this model.</p>

<p>One of the ways that social workers facilitate social change in community practice is to provide testimony to decision-making bodies such as neighborhood associations, city councils, departments at the local or state level, and state legislatures. Preparing and providing testimony is a strategy that can be used in conjunction with any of the community intervention models. Quick Guide 33 provides details on preparing and presenting testimony.</p>

<h3 id="providing-testimony">Providing Testimony</h3>

<p>Social workers often provide testimony to legislative and planning committees at the local, state, regional, and national levels. The main purpose of testimony is to share information and advocate for evidence-based solutions. The following steps are helpful when preparing to provide testimony to a legislative body:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Learn about how legislative proposals (bills) work their way through the legislature. Who sponsored or co-sponsored the bill? To what committee(s) has your bill been assigned? What are the possible outcomes of committee work on the bill? Where will the bill go next if the committee approves it? Has a similar bill been introduced in the other chamber?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Learn about the history of the topic and bill. Has this bill been proposed before? Who sponsored it? What happened to the bill? Did the general public already vote on the topic through a referendum? Has this bill already been amended?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Engage in research about the topic. Research existing statutes that the bill seeks to amend, revise, supplement, or delete. If possible, research the cost of the bill, if enacted. A “fiscal note” is often prepared by staff members of the legislative body to estimate the potential costs in some detail.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Engage in research about the politics of the bill. Which individuals or what groups are working for the bill? Against the bill? What are their perspectives?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Research the committee membership. Who is the chair? What is his/her perspective on the topic of your bill? Who else is on the committee? What are their interests and those of their constituents? How have they voted on this topic before?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Determine how long your testimony should be, and, depending on time, draft a written statement that: (1) provides factual data, including cost estimates, needed to support the desired policy changes; (2) analyzes the proposed changes/additions to present law; (3) discusses how the desired policy changes would alleviate community problems, and any possible new problems that various attempts to do so may create; and/or (4) provides suggestions for needed amendments to changes that have been previously suggested.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>When delivering your testimony, consider the following:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Use effective nonverbal communication. Dress professionally, make eye contact, and display a calm and confident demeanor.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Start your testimony by introducing yourself and the organization you represent. Use full titles to address committee members. At the beginning and end of your testimony, thank the committee chair and decision-makers for allowing you to speak. State your name and background information related to the topic at hand (such as where you live, your credentials, or your connection to the topic). Clearly state your request for the outcome of the decision-making process.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Describe your involvement with the topic, including any helpful context or background. If the testimony is related to your employment, provide your employer’s name and interest in the topic.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Describe how the topic affects you, your clients, and members of your community. Provide factual information as well as anecdotes. Describe how the pending decision will positively or negatively affect you, your clients, and members of your community, and include a description of who will benefit, or who will be hurt, by the decision.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>End by thanking the committee again, and offer to be of further assistance. Offer to leave a copy of your written statement with the committee.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Convey passion for the topic you are addressing, balanced with professionalism.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If you are asked questions, maintain your professionalism. Do not take questions personally, but rather state facts and your position on the bill. Offer to get facts or call on someone else to help, if needed.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Remember that a vote can be the result of a particular amendment to the bill, budget projections, position of party leadership, or complex interrelationships between procedural and substantive issues—not necessarily the subject of the bill. This means that it is important not to assume that votes against the community’s interest are the result of lack of support for the community at other times or on other issues.</p>

<p>Source: Kleinkauf, 1981; Oregon Legislature, n.d.; University of Kansas Work Group for Community Health and Development, 2018.</p>

<h2 id="blending-models">Blending Models</h2>

<p>While we present models here in a “pure” form, in practice strategies from various models are often used together in community practice. For this reason, it is important for social workers in community practice to know about and plan to use parts of all of the models as needed (Rothman, 2008; Weil &amp; Gamble, 2009). We present examples of using strategies from different models, or blending the models, in this section.</p>

<h3 id="blending-the-planningpolicy-and-community-capacity-development-models">Blending the planning/policy and Community Capacity development Models</h3>

<p>It is possible to blend the planning/policy model and the community capacity development model with the use of citizen input and a data-driven planning process. For example, the St. Louis Mental Health Board in Missouri periodically completes a needs assessment of local mental health services to identify unmet needs. The Board then creates a multiyear plan to allocate funding to best meet those needs. Throughout the process, the Board receives feedback from mental health providers and citizens, including those who receive mental health services. In this way, the Board uses strategies from two models through the strong reliance on data (planning/policy) and the use of citizen and provider input into the planning process (community capacity development) (Rothman, 2008).</p>

<p>Another example of using strategies from different models can be seen in social work practice within <strong>community development corporations (CDCs)</strong>, which are resident-driven organizations that exist to provide assistance to the community. This assistance can include facilitating housing improvements throughout the community, supporting businesses and commercial real estate efforts, and involvement in improving child care availability, community centers, and other community resources. Boards of residents, business owners, and local government officials generally govern CDCs. They often use data-informed approaches in creating small-business assistance programs, helping to establish cooperatives, which are member-owned and -operated businesses, or rehabilitating affordable housing in the community (Garkovich, 2011).</p>

<h3 id="blending-the-social-advocacy-and-planningpolicy-models">Blending the social advocacy and planning/policy Models</h3>
<p>This is done by emphasizing the use of data and logic in policy advocacy efforts. For instance, social workers in community practice often work with residents in using data from needs assessments and funding allocation plans to advocate for policy changes at the local or state levels in educating decision-makers and engaging in citizen lobbying efforts as needed. In this manner, community practice efforts can involve both the use of data (planning/policy) and advocacy efforts (social advocacy) to facilitate community change (Rothman, 2008). This blend can best describe the efforts of many prominent social justice pioneers in history, such as Jane Addams, John Dewey, Margaret Sanger, and Ida B. Wells-Barnett. These pioneers based their arguments about social ills such as child labor, lynching, inadequate housing codes, laws against birth control, and many other issues on data and logical arguments. Using tactics associated with different models that bring pressure to bear on decision-makers (social advocacy) with data and logic (planning/policy) most closely aligns with the roots of the profession (Rothman, 2008). Today, “think-tanks” such as the Urban Institute and the New America Foundation provide well-researched factual reports that social advocacy groups use to work for change.</p>

<h3 id="blending-the-social-advocacy-and-community-capacity-development-models">Blending the social advocacy and Community Capacity development Models</h3>
<p>By blending these models, networks of community stakeholders are encouraged to advocate with leaders, elected officials, and other decision-makers to improve the community. For example, a neighborhood group may learn about the plans to establish a landfill that would accept some toxic waste in their community and decide to fight it by lobbying key decision-makers, delivering petitions, and/ or picketing the local government. A group of parents of children who are lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and queer (LGBTQ+) may decide to engage in an online effort to advocate for civil rights for LGBTQ+ people in their community. If their elected officials and key decision-makers in public offices responsible for civil rights protections are not responsive, the parent group may plan a more public action such as a sit-in at a strategic location to advocate for the support they need. This approach emphasizes building community capacity with social advocacy techniques in situations where this mix will maximize the possibility for community change (Rothman, 2008). The use of strategies associated with community capacity development and social advocacy together is common in long-term social change efforts such as the LGBTQ+ rights, environmental, and women’s rights movements. Strategically using social advocacy techniques while building the capacities of community members helps create an aptitude for long-term involvement in community intervention (Rothman, 2008).</p>

<h1 id="skills-for-community-intervention">Skills for community intervention</h1>

<p>Community intervention involves social work practice to improve community conditions and quality of life for neighborhood residents or community members. We discuss community social and economic development, asset building and asset mapping, and community organizing. We also cover the skills of conducting meetings and facilitating decision-making in community practice.</p>

<h2 id="community-social-and-economic-development">Community social and economic development</h2>

<p>Community social and economic development (hereafter referred to as “community development”), also called “locality development” and “community building,” is an often-ambiguous term with a variety of definitions. In this text, it is a community intervention method that seeks to maximize human potential by focusing on social relationships and the environment to improve the physical and social fabric of communities (Rubin &amp; Rubin, 2008). Community development emphasizes social development through relationship building, education, motivation for self-help, and leadership development. It encourages local participation in community efforts toward the goal of strengthening democracy at the local community level and can include efforts to revitalize institutions. Community development that is focused on economics includes economic development, affordable housing, employment services, and other activities. Often community social development and community economic development efforts are simultaneous and interdependent, and they can be viewed as a continuum.</p>

<p>Community development may include professions from many fields in addition to social work, including business, sociology, anthropology, psychology, and others (Gamble &amp; Hoff, 2013). Community development work most closely aligns with the community capacity development model discussed earlier, because its goal is to mobilize communities to solve problems and effectively work with institutions rather than to engage in social advocacy or planning/policy work. However, community development work also can use a mix of models, depending on the needs at the time.</p>

<p>The following assumptions drive community development (Cnaan &amp; Rothman, 2008, pp. 247–248):</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>People may need to become aware of a common problem and create a desire to act in order to solve problems.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>A diverse group of people across various dimensions of diversity (i.e., race, ethnicity, socioeconomic status, etc.) adds value and authenticity to the efforts and ensures that they serve the interests of more than one group of people.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Democratic decision-making and participatory democracy values and fosters local self-determination.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Empowerment, or the capacity to solve problems by working with the authorities and institutions that affect the lives of community members, is a central goal of community development.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The primary constituents of the community development social worker are community members and community organizations, rather than those who hold more power.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Planned change is preferred to inaction that allows current conditions to continue.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="community-development-skills">Community development skills</h2>

<p>The most commonly used practice skills are group work skills. Group work, covered extensively in Chapters 8 and 9, is a major part of community development work, as this type of work is often conducted in meetings. To ensure success, community development social workers must employ task group work skills including leadership; communication; problem-solving; and managing group function and processes such as educating, forming groups, seeking consensus, encouraging group discussion, and focusing to solve concerns and problems common to the group. Other skills include analyzing community issues and facilitating the increase of communication among community members (Cnaan &amp; Rothman, 2008).</p>

<p>As discussed in Chapter 9, promoting leadership from within the community in social work directed at community development requires the ability to distribute leadership as widely as possible. Facilitation of effective task meetings is one example of a leadership skill that social workers may use or teach to community leaders. Quick Guide 34 provides an overview of the tasks involved in effective meeting facilitation. These tasks can be distributed among individuals during meetings or handled by a small group in preparation for a larger meeting as a way to learn and exercise leadership skills.</p>

<h3 id="quick-guide-34-elements-of-effective-meetings">QUICK GUIDE 34 Elements of Effective Meetings</h3>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Stage</th>
      <th>Element</th>
      <th>Notes</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Preparation</td>
      <td>Goals</td>
      <td>Develop goals for each meeting</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Site</td>
      <td>Establish a meeting site that is familiar, accessible, perceived as safe, and has parking.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Date/Timing</td>
      <td>Set a date and time that is convenient for the majority of prospective participants.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Facilitator</td>
      <td>Involve the facilitator in setting the agenda.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Agenda</td>
      <td>Include information about each item, the name of the person who is introducing the item, and a time limit. Discuss easy items first, followed by hard and then moderate decisions.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Food</td>
      <td>Offer food and drinks in ways that are least disruptive.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Recruitment/Turnout</td>
      <td>Use word-of-mouth and written meeting announcements, and remind people a few days prior to the meeting.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Meeting Roles</td>
      <td>Assign roles ahead of time, including facilitator, note taker, timekeeper, presenter, and greeter.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Room Logistics</td>
      <td>Set up chairs, AV equipment, flipchart, sign-in table, food/drink, and microphone early enough to check the equipment.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Background Materials</td>
      <td>Prepare background materials about pending decisions and preliminary proposals to discuss.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Meeting</td>
      <td>Timeliness</td>
      <td>Begin and end the meeting on time.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Welcome,Introduce</td>
      <td>Begin with a warm welcome and introductions to set a positive tone, regardless of the turnout.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Agenda</td>
      <td>Review the agenda with the group and make changes as needed.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Meeting Rules</td>
      <td>Explain any rules, including decision-making rules.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Discussion</td>
      <td>Encourage discussion of various viewpoints; encourage all to speak by drawing out quieter people, limiting those who dominate, and encouraging respect for viewpoints; summarize; and bring closure to discussion.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Focus</td>
      <td>Bring the group back to the agenda if the discussion wanders.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Endings</td>
      <td>Summarize meeting results, decisions, and needed follow-up. Thank people for attending.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Follow-up</td>
      <td>Notes</td>
      <td>Prepare and disseminate meeting notes quickly.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Think people</td>
      <td>Contact people, especially new people, to thank them for their contribution to the meeting, to encourage follow-up on commitments for action, and to encourage them to attend the next meeting.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Source: Adapted from Bobo, Kendall, &amp; Max, 2010; Minieri &amp; Getsos, 2007</p>

<p>In task groups, using decision-making processes that promote full participation is important. Decision-making for groups can be handled in many ways, including the ==parliamentary procedures==, sometimes known as ==Robert’s Rules of Order==, and ==consensus decision-making==. Quick Guide 35 provides an overview of Robert’s Rules of Order, and Quick Guide 36 provides an overview of consensus decision-making. Both types of decision-making processes are common in task groups, depending on the context of the work. Social workers need to be familiar with decision-making processes to fully participate as individuals and to help others participate.</p>

<p>Recruitment of new participants is an ongoing and important community development skill. Participants involved in community development work are often volunteers, and recruiting, training, monitoring, and rewarding volunteers is important to the success of long-term goals. The most effective ways to recruit participants include focusing on people who are most likely to join, using a well-formed recruiting message, using multiple recruitment methods, providing orientation for new participants, and making it easy to join activities. Volunteer activities have to be calibrated to fit the skills, time, and interests of volunteers and be meaningful to them (Cnaan &amp; Rothman, 2008).</p>

<h3 id="quick-guide-35-utilizing-roberts-rules-of-order">QUICK GUIDE 35 Utilizing Robert’s Rules of Order</h3>

<p>Many formal groups, such as boards of directors, committees, and policy-making groups, often use some form of a formal decision-making process. Parliamentary procedures, or Robert’s Rules of Order, are often used because they are well known, help to maintain order, and allow actions to be taken in an expedient and consistent manner. Although the process can be quite complex, some groups utilize the general rules without learning the minutiae. Understanding the major concepts of parliamentary procedure is a critical social work skill for facilitating and participating in a meeting.</p>

<p>Robert’s Rules of Order provide a structured, democratic (majority rules) mechanism whereby formal groups can engage in efficient and fair decision-making. The following are major elements of the process:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The use of a motion to introduce a proposal. Any idea for the group’s consideration must be introduced as a motion (i.e., “I move that …”). Only one motion can be considered at a time.</li>
  <li>The seconding of a motion to move a proposal forward for discussion. A motion cannot move forward in the process unless someone other than the person who made the motion “seconds” the motion (i.e., “I second the motion”). Without a second, a motion dies and is not discussed.</li>
  <li>The use of open discussion to enable participants to present perspectives and ask questions about a motion. After a motion is made and seconded, the facilitator can open discussion about the motion, and group members can ask questions of the people who made and seconded the motion.</li>
  <li>Amendments to reflect revisions to an original motion based on the debate/discussion. During the discussion, one or more participants may offer an amendment to clarify or narrow the motion. This amendment must be voted on before the original motion is voted on. A majority vote is required to pass an amendment.</li>
  <li>Majority rules (i.e., a minimum of 51 percent of members agreeing) to establish a motion as a decision.</li>
</ul>

<p>Source: Adapted from Robert, Honemann, &amp; Balch, 2011</p>

<h3 id="quick-guide-36-utilizing-consensus-for-decision-making">QUICK GUIDE 36 Utilizing Consensus for Decision-Making</h3>

<p>Real change, at the individual, family, group, community, or organizational level, comes from individuals who are highly committed to a decision or direction in which they fully participated. Consensus decision-making, or a cooperative process in which all members develop and agree to support a decision that is in the best interests of the whole group, can be effective in situations in which the following conditions are present:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Participants feel a genuine stake in the decision.</li>
  <li>Participants share a common purpose and values.</li>
  <li>Participants trust each other.</li>
  <li>Participants are willing to put the best interests of the group over personal preferences.</li>
  <li>Participants can share their ideas and opinions freely, without fear of ridicule.</li>
  <li>Enough time is available for the process.</li>
  <li>Participants can engage in active listening and consider different points of view.</li>
</ul>

<p>After preparing for the meeting, the process helps meeting participants:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Explore the issue toward the goal of developing an informed, shared understanding of the facts and the issue.</li>
  <li>Establish decision criteria, including such factors as interests/needs that must be met, resource constraints, and possible ramifications of decisions.</li>
  <li>Develop and discuss a written preliminary proposal.</li>
  <li>Test for consensus, asking participants whether they can live with the proposal (original or amended), whether it meets the decision criteria, and whether it is the best decision possible.</li>
  <li>Reach agreement by restating the proposed decision and ensuring that participants can support the implementation of the proposal.</li>
</ul>

<p>Source: Adapted from Dressler, 2006</p>

<h1 id="a-generalist-approach-to-community-intervention">A Generalist approach to Community intervention</h1>

<p>Depending on the context of the community intervention, generalist social workers often integrate aspects of community organizing and community development activities into their practice. For example, social workers can help community members develop a shared identity, interpersonal bonds, skills for public discourse, the ability to determine priorities and work on common challenges together, as well as leadership skills. All of these must be developed for community change efforts to be possible. Social workers can play an important role in helping develop these prerequisites. Further, social workers who work primarily with individuals, families, and groups have opportunities to support the development of these skills and to encourage people to participate in community efforts.</p>

<p>Social workers can help build the capacity of individuals to engage in community interventions in many ways. At the interpersonal level, social workers emphasize collaboration with both clients and community members to optimize rights, strengths, and capabilities. Social workers discuss power and control with clients and community members to increase awareness of these dynamics in everyday life and in community activities. As first suggested by Paulo Freire (1973), educating people about social conditions, patterns of resource distribution, oppression, and other social and environmental realities, and using respectful discussion and questioning, can help and support people to engage in collective action.</p>

<p>==Social workers strive to provide evidence-based interventions in community practice==. Creating a body of research to inform evidence-based practice has proven challenging due to the complexity of community interventions, the difficulties of community research, and many organizations’ lack of capacity to engage in research. Yet social workers must conduct or locate research before intervening. Quick Guide 37 lists sample resources for locating evidence on community practice interventions. Exhibit 11.6 provides research findings about the most effective community intervention activities that social workers undertake (Ohmer &amp; Korr, 2006).</p>

<p>Social workers also engage in social planning efforts when they participate in proposing that elected officials or human service planning councils take action. They engage by writing letters, testifying to committees, becoming members of planning committees, and/or organizing others to lobby planning councils. As part of that process, social workers can carefully create opportunities for community members to participate so that their participation is meaningful and effective, rather than a token effort to “involve” residents. For example, social workers can invite community residents to testify at public hearings about proposals to close schools in their neighborhoods and help prepare them to testify. Social workers can also seek resident involvement in neighborhood committees and work to ensure that residents can voice their opinions, participate fully in decision-making, and assist to implement decisions. Social workers can also make connections between people in disparate situations, so that the needs of individuals are connected to broader efforts and wider structures. For example, if a social worker encounters a resident whose child has lead poisoning, the social worker may be able to link this “case” to a broader “cause” of a community problem with lead poisoning due to the old housing stock in the neighborhood and the reluctance of landlords to remediate the lead in their units. Social workers can also invite residents to participate in community-wide efforts to alleviate and prevent the problem, such as lead paint screenings in schools and programs to help tenants test for lead paint in their apartments.</p>

<h3 id="examples-of-efforts-to-promote-evidence-based-community-practice">Examples of Efforts to Promote Evidence-Based Community Practice</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Children, Families, and Communities</li>
</ul>

<p>Harvard Family Research Project, Harvard Graduate School of Education. The Education Resources Information Center (ERIC) contains new studies on programs and policies, particularly those focused on children, families, and communities. Available at https://eric.ed.gov/.</p>

<p>Society for Child and Family Policy and Practice, Division 37 of the American Psychological Association (APA). The Society provides information about services and service structures for children and youth. See www.apa.org/about/division/div37.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Community Change</li>
</ul>

<p>The Aspen Institute report, Building Knowledge about Community Change, summarizes key learning about how to evaluate community change initiatives and how to identify strategies for enhancing the evidence base for improving conditions in low-income communities. Available at www.aspeninstitute. org/publications/building-knowledge-about-community-change-moving-beyond-evaluation/.</p>

<p>Society for Community Research and Action, Division 27 of the American Psychological Association (APA). The Society provides access to research on community interventions. See www.apa.org/about/ division/div27.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Early Childhood, health Care, and housing</li>
</ul>

<p>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention’s The Guide to Community Preventive Services includes systematic reviews of interventions in early childhood development programs, culturally competent health care, and housing. Available at www.thecommunityguide.org.</p>

<ul>
  <li>General evidence-Based resources for Community practice</li>
</ul>

<p>The Campbell Collaboration promotes positive social change through the production and use of systematic reviews and other evidence synthesis for evidence-based policy and practice. Available at campbellcollaboration.org.</p>

<p>Laura and John Arnold Foundation Evidence-Based Policy and Innovation. This nonprofit organization is committed to evidence-based social policies and programs. See www.arnoldventures. org/work/evidence-based-policy.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Housing</li>
</ul>

<p>U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD). HUD has done much research on housing issues, and reports are available at www.huduser.gov/portal/reports/home.html.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Mental health in Communities</li>
</ul>

<p>National Registry of Evidence-based Programs and Practices (NREPP). Sponsored by the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration, NREPP is an online, searchable registry of evidence-based mental health and substance use interventions. Available at www.samhsa.gov/ebp-resource-center</p>

<ul>
  <li>Violence prevention</li>
</ul>

<p>The Center for the Study and Prevention of Violence (CSPV), University of Colorado at Boulder provides research on effective violence prevention. Available at https://cspv.colorado.edu/</p>

<p>Sources: Updated from Ohmer, 2008 and Thyer, 2008</p>

<h3 id="exhibit-116-effectiveness-of-community-practice">EXHIBIT 11.6 Effectiveness of Community Practice</h3>

<p>Community practice interventions are often complex, with multiple community locations, goals, and activities that make them difficult to evaluate. However, scholars suggest that community practice interventions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>have a positive impact on facilitating citizen participation, including increasing collective action and community involvement;</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>facilitate personal and collective competencies among participants, including increasing self-esteem, personal and community empowerment, leadership and political skills, and community pride and belonging;</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>have a positive impact on improving the physical, social, and economic conditions of communities (i.e., creating and improving affordable housing; increasing home ownership, improving infrastructure and physical appearance; increasing income, investment, and employment; improving high school education; and reducing the sale of alcohol to and its use among young people);</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>are often unable to find statistically significant effects (many studies indicate that interventions do not affect the physical and economic attributes of the communities); and</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>increase the likelihood of involving the community organizing efforts of older female residents, African Americans, and Hispanics.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>other factors that help to explain and predict citizen participation include interest in the problems the intervention was attempting to solve, neighborhood perceptions and relationships, and length of residency.</p>

<p>Community practice interventions more easily improve citizen participation and associated benefits (i.e., improving collective action and personal and political skills of participants) than they improve complex physical, social, and economic problems in poor communities. Therefore, social work strategies should simultaneously focus on developing ways to strengthen citizen participation and on building the capacity of individuals.</p>

<p>Source: Ohmer &amp; Korr, 2006</p>

<h1 id="evaluation-of-social-work-practice-with-communities">evaluation of social work practice with Communities</h1>

<p>Similar to evaluation with individuals, families, and groups, evaluation of social work community practice interventions can assess the process along the way (i.e., ==process evaluation==); the extent to which goals were achieved (i.e., ==outcome evaluation==); and the social worker’s skills in the intervention phase. Evaluation seeks to determine the value of the intervention and differs from simply monitoring one’s practice (Netting et al., 2017). Just as the community change effort is a collaborative process, so too is the evaluation. Community participation is important throughout the change effort to empower participants. Similarly, community members who are able to collaborate as equal partners in evaluation are likely to feel a deserved sense of ownership in the process.</p>

<p>The evaluation process begins as an element of the intervention design and may be predetermined by an organization, a funder, or a public entity. It requires social workers and community members first to determine: (1) whether both the process and outcomes will be evaluated, (2) the ways in which the process and outcomes will be evaluated, and (3) the means by which data will be collected as the basis for the evaluation. Evaluation of community change efforts may include documentation of individual, interpersonal, and community processes and outcomes. Preferably, the evaluation process will include both qualitative and quantitative data to provide information about the process of community change and progress on the desired outcomes at the individual, interpersonal, and community levels.</p>

<h1 id="critical-considerations-in-community-intervention-termination-evaluation-and-follow-up">Critical Considerations in Community intervention, termination, evaluation, and follow-up</h1>

<p>Community social work practice, including the intervention, termination, evaluation, and follow-up phases, offers many rewards and challenges. One challenging aspect of some types of community social work practice is long hours. For example, community social work practice can involve working during the day with professionals in organizations and institutions and in the evenings and on weekends with community participants. Efforts to change institutions, policies, and practices can take a long time, and there may be many setbacks along the way. Tangible rewards and successes for the work may be few and far between, which can lead to burnout unless social workers have a solid understanding of practice at the community level (Rubin &amp; Rubin, 2008).</p>

<p>Rewards include the satisfaction of working to change environments to better meet the needs of, and to provide empowerment opportunities for, individuals and communities. Many community practitioners appreciate the ability to partner with individuals, families, and groups to better their lives, while avoiding the view of persons as clients, which can involve diagnostic labels, treatment plans, and a primarily individualistic perspective. In community practice, community members are involved in making decisions that affect their lives, sometimes for the first time. Helping people gain their voices and work toward large-scale social change is work toward social justice. The variety of tasks completed, the joy of successes, and the autonomy and flexibility are other factors that attract social workers to community practice (Rubin &amp; Rubin, 2008).</p>

<p>Community practitioners must have the energy for long-term work and must be able to see value in the process and effort involved, rather than just in the outcomes. The occasional victories, even short-term or small, along with the benefits of working with and on behalf of entire communities, must be enough to sustain community practitioners. Community practitioners must celebrate small gains. They must often work diligently on short-term or immediate goals, while keeping the larger, systemic, institutional change in focus.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Social work Practice" /><category term="研究" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[書籍 Birkenmaier, J., &amp; Berg-Weger, M. (2020). The practice of generalist social work. Routledge.P496-527]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">日本におけるコミュニティワーク理論の再構築 （池本賢一 2019）</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/%E3%82%B3%E3%83%9F%E3%83%A5%E3%83%8B%E3%83%86%E3%82%A3%E3%83%AF%E3%83%BC%E3%82%AF/2023/04/16/%E6%97%A5%E6%9C%AC%E3%82%B3%E3%83%9F%E3%83%A5%E3%83%8B%E3%83%86%E3%82%A3%E3%83%AF%E3%83%BC%E3%82%AF%E5%8F%82%E8%80%83%E6%96%87%E7%8C%AE.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="日本におけるコミュニティワーク理論の再構築 （池本賢一 2019）" /><published>2023-04-16T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2023-04-16T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/%E3%82%B3%E3%83%9F%E3%83%A5%E3%83%8B%E3%83%86%E3%82%A3%E3%83%AF%E3%83%BC%E3%82%AF/2023/04/16/%E6%97%A5%E6%9C%AC%E3%82%B3%E3%83%9F%E3%83%A5%E3%83%8B%E3%83%86%E3%82%A3%E3%83%AF%E3%83%BC%E3%82%AF%E5%8F%82%E8%80%83%E6%96%87%E7%8C%AE</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/%E3%82%B3%E3%83%9F%E3%83%A5%E3%83%8B%E3%83%86%E3%82%A3%E3%83%AF%E3%83%BC%E3%82%AF/2023/04/16/%E6%97%A5%E6%9C%AC%E3%82%B3%E3%83%9F%E3%83%A5%E3%83%8B%E3%83%86%E3%82%A3%E3%83%AF%E3%83%BC%E3%82%AF%E5%8F%82%E8%80%83%E6%96%87%E7%8C%AE.html"><![CDATA[<script type="module"> import mermaid from 'https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/mermaid@10.0.2/+esm'; mermaid.initialize({ startOnLoad: true }); </script>

<h1 id="文献">文献</h1>

<p>池本賢一・村山浩一郎（2019）「我が国におけるコミュニティワーク理論の再構築に向けた試論ーコミュニティワークの定義及び範囲に着目してー」『福岡県立大学人間社会学部紀要』27(2), 45-58.</p>

<h1 id="要旨">要旨</h1>

<p>今日のわが国における社会福祉制度の動向を鑑みると、各福祉分野で地域支援が重要視されていると考えられる。しかしながら、これまで==地域支援の方法論とされてきたコミュニティワークは、概念や展開プロセス、用いる技術等が必ずしも明確化されていない==という課題がある。本稿は、これまでのコミュニティワークに関する研究から、特に==定義及び範囲に着目して整理を行い、それらを踏まえた上で、理論の再構築に向けた試論を提示==するものである。先行研究の検討から、「ニーズ·資源調整」、「インター·グループ·ワーク」、「統合」、「組織化」、「計画·政策」、「ソーシャル·アクション」、「アドミニストレーション」、「個別課題を踏まえた地域支援」、「主体形成とプログラム開発とその循環」がコミュニティワーク理論のキー概念として明らかになり、これらを基にコミュニティワークの体系図の提示を行った。</p>

<h1 id="キーワード">キーワード</h1>

<p>コミュニティオーガニゼーション、コミュニティワーク、社会福祉協議会、地域福祉、地域支援</p>

<h1 id="研究の背景と課題の所在">研究の背景と課題の所在</h1>

<p>今日、わが国の社会福祉の様々な領域において、地域づくりが重要視されており、それらの動向を集約する形で2017年に社会福祉法が改正された。同法においては、==包括的な支援体制の構築などが明記され、地域共生社会の実現に向けた法改正が進められている。このことからも、住民同士の支え合いの醸成、分野横断的なサービス提供体制の構築などの地域づくりに取り組むこと==が求められているといえる。</p>

<p>このような、地域を支援する方法論にコミュニティワークがある。コミュニティワークについて、瓦井（2011）は「1987年に社会福祉士及び介護福祉士法が成立して以降は、用語としてコミュニティワークが定着しましたが、それでも理論的に統一された定義は未だに見られません」と述べており、理論的に確立しているとは言い難い状況にある。様々な福祉分野が地域を志向しているわが国の福祉施策の動向を踏まえると、==コミュニティワークの理論を明確化することは喫緊の課題==である。</p>

<p>定義が理論的に確立していないという課題を残す一方で、わが国の社会福祉士養成に関わるテキストでは、コミュニティワークの記述が減少し、代わりにコミュニティソーシャルワークの記述が増加している。また、研究論文においても、==近年コミュニティワークに関する研究が減少傾向にある==と金田は指摘している（金田2016)。</p>

<p>また、コミュニティソーシャルワークとコミュニティワークの関係性に関しては、==コミュニティソーシャルワークがコミュニティワークを包含するか否かなど、出口の見えない議論が続いており、コミュニティワークの曖昧さは地域福祉の援助技術に関する研究を進める上で、大きな阻害要因になっている==。</p>

<p>このことから、コミュニティワークに残された課題、すなわち定義や技術体系化に関する研究を進めていく必要があると考える。これを踏まえ、本稿はこれまでのコミュニティワークに関する研究から、特に定義と範囲に着目して整理を行い、それらを踏まえた上で、今後の理論研究の一つの方向性を示すものとして、試論ではあるが、コミュニティワークの定義、及び体系図の提示を行った。</p>

<h1 id="平野のコミュニティワーク">平野のコミュニティワーク</h1>

<p>平野（2003）も、コミュニティワークの展開プロセスとして==永田（幹）の「活動主体の組織化→問題把握→計画策定→計画実施→評価」==を示している。平野はさらに、コミュニティワークの実践プロセス整理において、活動主体の組織化とサービス資源の開発は区別されているものの、循環的な視点が弱いと指摘し、S⇔ Pモデルという実践モデルを提唱している。</p>

<p>永田（幹）</p>
<div class="mermaid">
```mermaid
flowchart LR
活動主体の組織化==&gt;問題把握==&gt;計画策定==&gt;計画実施==&gt;評価
```
</div>

<p>活動主体とプログラムの循環（平野2008:104）</p>
<div class="mermaid">
```mermaid
flowchart LR
1.組織化---&gt;2.把握---&gt;3.作成---&gt;4.実施---&gt;5.評価---&gt;1.組織化
subgraph one
活動主体:S===1.組織化
end
subgraph two
プログラム:M===3.作成
プログラム:M===4.実施
end
```
</div>

<p>平野は永田（幹）の示した地域組織化過程をベースに、コミュニティワーカーが活動主体の組織化に関わり、プログラム作成を支援するという「援助実践」にウェイトを置いた循環構造として、図2を示している。</p>

<p>平野の図では、活動主体を組織化し、プログラムを作成·実施するという循環を生み出すもの（また、それを支援するもの）としてコミュニティワークが位置付けられている。</p>

<p>つまり、平野は永田（幹）の地域組織化過程を踏まえてはいるものの、地域組織化をコミュニティワークとして捉えるのではなく、一連の循環を繰り返すことによって、メゾ領域からマクロ領域へと活動を波及させていく螺旋構造の循環がコミュニティワークにはあるとしている。</p>

<h1 id="永田祐のコミュニティワーク">永田（祐）のコミュニティワーク</h1>

<p>永田（祐）は、平野の示した図をもとに、以下のように述べている。地域組織化のプロセスは、（1）地域（コミュニティ）の問題状況の把握、（2）活動主体の組織化、（3）プログラムの作成と、（4）実施、そして（5）評価というプロセスに整理できる（永田2017：86）。</p>

<p>永田（祐）はコミュニティワークの展開を論じる上で、最後にソーシャルアクションについて言及している。また、永田（祐）はコミュニティワーク＝地域組織化とは捉えておらず、あくまでも地域組織化をコミュニティワークの中心的な実践と位置づけ、論述している。</p>

<p>さらに、永田（祐）の論述では、個別課題を踏まえたコミュニティワークの展開を考える上で、個別課題を普遍化するための「場」が必要であると述べている。永田（祐）は、その課題の普遍化に必要な「場」や「機会」をつくり、学び、活動、計画への反映などの行動を起こすためには支援が必要であり、その一連の過程をコミュニティワークとし、今日的なコミュニティワークの方向性を示唆している。</p>

<p>永田（祐）のコミュニティワークは、個別課題を踏まえて展開される、いわばコミュニティソーシャルワークの考え方に近いものであるといえる。しかしながら、個別課題と地域課題を同時進行的に行うコミュニティソーシャルワークの概念とは異なり、地域支援がべースとなっている。このことから、個別課題を志向したコミュニティワークといえるが、その中で重要視しているのが「場」や「機会」の創出である。これまでのコミュニティワーク研究（澤田2006、長谷中2012など）や、永田（祐）の論述において住民が参加する「場」や「機会」をつくることの重要性は示されてきたものの、この「場」や「機会」をどのように構築するのかという方法·プロセスは、具体的な研究がなされていないという課題がある。</p>

<h1 id="まとめ">まとめ</h1>

<p>これまでのわが国におけるコミュニティワークの研究をまとめると、わが国においてはレイン報告、ニューステッター、ロスが示した3つのCOが統合される形で発展してきたと考えられる。そして、永田（幹）は当初、コミュニティワークを地域組織化とイコールで結ぶのではなく、広範な概念として提唱していたが、これまでコミュニティワークを用いて実践を重ねてきた社会福祉協議会においては、地域組織化活動として認識が広がってしまった可能性が示唆された。そして、平野は活動主体の組織化とプログラム作成·循環によるコミュニティワーク、永田（祐）は個別を見据えた地域支援としてコミュニティワークを論じ、野口はケースマネージメントを含む広範な活動としてコミュニティワークを捉えている。</p>

<p>また、英米と日本のコミュニティワークを比較すると、諸外国においては概念およびモデルの研究が主であり、展開プロセスを示したものがない。逆に、わが国においては展開プロセスを示したものが多く、モデルに関する論述は、鈴木（2002）、濱野（2004）、平野（2008）らが行っているが、英米と比較してもその数は少ない。この差は非常に興味深いものであるが、本稿の本旨ではないため今後の研究課題としたい。</p>

<h1 id="考察一コミュニティワークの整理と試論">考察一コミュニティワークの整理と試論</h1>

<p>これまで、コミュニティワークの定義、実践モデル、展開プロセスに関する先行研究を概観してきたが、統一された見解はなく、いずれも論者によってさまざまであることが窺えた。先行研究を踏まえると、英米からわが国に取入れられた概念として、「ニーズ·資源調整」、「インター·グループ·ワーク」、「統合」、「組織化」、「計画·政策」、「ソーシャル·アクション」、「アドミニストレーション」などがコミュニティワークの中に含まれていると考えられる。また、わが国におけるコミュニティワークでは、英米からの概念に加え、「個別課題を踏まえた地域支援」、「主体形成とプログラム開発、その循環」の概念が示されている。</p>

<p>これらを踏まえて、コミュニティワークを一つの体系図に示した（図4）。以下の体系図は、ミクロ·メゾ·マクロという圏域（活動の範囲）で整理したものである。なお、フィッシャーが示したように、「ソーシャルワーク外」の活動も考慮している。また、永田（幹）、野口、口スマンの論述に従って、マクロ圏域までを対象とした。</p>

<p>ここでは、図4の体系図について説明を行う。この体系図の特徴は、ミクロとメゾ、そしてマクロの間にそれぞれの圏域をつなぐ「結節点」があることである。これは、永田（祐そしてニューステッターによる論を参考に、今日の地域福祉実践を踏まえて設定を行った。まず、ソーシャルワークにおける、個人や世帯に対するケースワークなどの直接的な援助が行われる範囲をミクロ圏域とした。先述したように、永田（祐）は個別課題を見据えたコミュニティワークを考える上で、課題の普遍化を行うための「場·機会」をつくることの必要性を述べている。つまり、個別的な課題を地域の課題として転換する結節点としての「場·機会」が必要であるということである。それをミクロ圏域とメゾ圏域の中間に位置付けている。また、必ずしもミクロ圏域から課題を把握するわけではなく、地域アセスメントによる地域共通の課題を直接的に把握する場合もある。このことから、「個別課題の普遍化」と同様に「地域アセスメント」も活動主体の組織化につながる開始点に位置付けている。</p>

<p>次に、ソーシャルワークのメゾ圏域ではロスの統合化説が小地域に対する支援として有効であると考え、これを中核概念とした。ここでのメゾ圏域は自治会～小学校単位とし、永田（幹）の「地域組織化過程」を基本に、平野の循環構造を取り入れた形で示した。なお、本稿においては、地域アセスメントは支援者が行うもので、地域組織化過程の中の「問題の把握」2）は、住民がその問題を把握することと解釈し、区別して表している。</p>

<p>最後に、ソーシャルワークのマクロ圏域は、中学校区～自治体全域とし、政策·計画を位置付けた。政策や計画実行に際しての進行管理·運営管理が求められるため、ここにアドミニストレーションを位置付けている。そのメゾ圏域とマクロ圏域の中間も、これまでの先行研究を踏まえ、インター·グループ·ワークによる「場·機会」の設定（例えば、計画策定委員会など）や組織化を行う必要があり、これらを結節点として捉えた。ソーシャル·アクションについても、政策改善を促すために組織化を改めて行うことも想定されるため、この結節点にその組織化を位置付けている。なお、図の煩雑さを避けるために、政策や活動などが課題を抱える個人へ還元されるというべクトルも当然考慮すべきだが、ここでは割愛している。</p>

<p>次に、フィッシャーの論述にある「ソーシャルワーク外」のコミュニティワークについて述べる。フィッシャー（1987）は「ソーシャルワークモデル」を「地域社会を組織化したり、社会サービス組織間の連携を促したり、あるいは社会資源を開発したり、配分することを主な目標とする。最も特徴的なのは、COはそれ自体を一つの社会的事業として捉え、そしてソーシャル·ワーク専門職の一般的志向の範囲内で機能することである」と定義している。近年、ソーシャルワーカーの活動範囲としては想定されない、ソーシャルワーク外でまちづくりを行うNPOが増加している。彼らの活動は必ずしも地域の福祉課題のみに取り組んでいるわけではなく、地域の活性化など幅広く支援を行っている。トゥエルブトゥリーズ（2006）によると、イギリスでは福祉に限らず、広くまちづくりを支援するものとしてコミュニティワークが捉えられており、フィッシャーの示したソーシャルワークモデルにおける、ソーシャルワーク専門職の一般的志向の範囲外の活動が、コミュニティワークには含まれる。</p>

<p>このことから、ここでは環境、教育、保健など、福祉以外の分野において地域住民を組織化し、活動を支援していくものを「ソーシャルワーク外」のコミュニティワークとした。
この体系図を踏まえると、以下のようにコミュニティワークを定義できるのではないか。</p>

<p>コミュニティワークとは、地域に内在する諸課題を地域社会みずからが組織的に解決するために、地域の個別的·地域的課題を把握し、それらの諸課題が地域の課題として認識されるよう場·機会を設け、そこで相互作用によって地域の主体性を高め、課題解決のための実行計画立案を側面から支援し、必要に応じて地域の福祉活動に対して社会資源·関係機関との連絡調整、行政機関等に対する社会行動支援、政策への意見反映支援、計画の進行管理等を行う援助活動であり、それを進める方法と技術を含むものである。</p>

<p>これまで述べてきたように、先行研究では論者によってコミュニティワークに含める概念が異なっていた。そこで本稿では、それぞれの論述を矛盾なく組み合わせ、コミュニティワークの包括的な定義とその範囲を示す体系図の作成を試みた。近年重要視されている「包括的な支援体制」を踏まえ、「個別課題の普遍化」をコミュニティワークの概念に加え、最大限に広く定義と範囲を示した。これはあくまでもこれまでの先行研究をまとめた試論であるため、今後の研究において、各圏域における実践から、コミュニティワークに含まれる概念、定義、範囲、技術等を精査し、コミュニティワークの理論を検討していきたいと考えている。</p>

<h1 id="終わりに">終わりに</h1>

<p>今日の福祉施策の動向を踏まえると、地域支援の方法やプロセスを確立することは、社会福祉協議会だけでなく、多くのそれに携わる職員のスキルアップにつながる。しかしながら、これまで述べてきたように、地域支援の方法論として位置づけられているコミュニティワークは、その定義も未だ確立していない状況にある。今日求められているジェネラリストとしてのソーシャルワーカーを養成していく上でも、コミュニティワークの理論の確立は重要な課題であると考える。
本稿で示した定義及び体系図は試論に過ぎないが、今後の研究の一つの道標になると考える。</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="コミュニティワーク" /><category term="研究" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">230415 小山セミナー ミニ発表</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/%E5%B0%8F%E5%B1%B1%E3%82%BB%E3%83%9F%E3%83%8A%E3%83%BC/2023/04/14/230415-%E5%B0%8F%E5%B1%B1%E3%82%BB%E3%83%9F%E3%83%8A%E3%83%BC.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="230415 小山セミナー ミニ発表" /><published>2023-04-14T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2023-04-14T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/%E5%B0%8F%E5%B1%B1%E3%82%BB%E3%83%9F%E3%83%8A%E3%83%BC/2023/04/14/230415%20%E5%B0%8F%E5%B1%B1%E3%82%BB%E3%83%9F%E3%83%8A%E3%83%BC</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/%E5%B0%8F%E5%B1%B1%E3%82%BB%E3%83%9F%E3%83%8A%E3%83%BC/2023/04/14/230415-%E5%B0%8F%E5%B1%B1%E3%82%BB%E3%83%9F%E3%83%8A%E3%83%BC.html"><![CDATA[<h4 id="研究背景">研究背景</h4>
<p>中国における社会課題解決に資する地域介入実践研究は、2010年代に入り徐々に活発となっている。そのうち、大半はアメリカのコミュニティ・オーガニゼーション（CO）研究者であるジャック・ロスマンが提唱されたコミュニティ・インターベンション理論を活用したうえで、コミュニティに存在するボランティア参加、待機児童、住宅問題、貧困、ホームレス、環境保全、社会的孤立などさまざまな社会課題を解決するために社会的介入プログラムという形式で行われている。しかしながら、社会課題に応じる地域介入実践の効果を評価する必要性が論じられているが、どのような方法で評価するのが妥当なのか、いわゆる評価方法論が未だに確立されていない状況にある。そのため、社会的介入プログラムの効果をシステマティックに検討できるプログラム評価の活用を視野に入れている。</p>

<h4 id="ロスマンのコミュニティインターベンション理論3つの実践モデルrothman-200712">ロスマンのコミュニティ・インターベンション理論（3つの実践モデル）（Rothman 2007:12）</h4>
<ol>
  <li>「プランニング／ポリシー」は、データ駆動型（Date-driven）アプローチである。データをはじめ経験的な事実によって明らかにされた真実が伝わることが説得力となり，その結果，解決策を提案・実行することにつながるとしている。</li>
  <li>「コミュニティ・キャパシティ・ディベロップメント」は、問題の影響を受けている人々が知識やスキルを身につけることによって、彼ら自身の問題をよりよく理解し、問題を克服するために協働しようるとき、最もよく変化を起こすことができると想定している。したがって、このアプローチは、戦術（tactic）へのコンセンサス、そして媒介や成果としての社会的連帯があることによって成立すると述べている。</li>
  <li>「ソーシャル・アドボカシー」は、問題を引き起こしたり問題の解決を阻害したり人々・制度に対しては、圧力を活用して活動を展開することが最善の方法とされている。</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="プログラム評価">プログラム評価</h4>
<p>プログラム評価とは，社会調査手法を活用し，社会的介入プログラムの有効性を体系的に調査するものである。その評価は，プログラムを取り巻く政策的・組織的な文脈を考慮して行われるもので，社会状況を改善するための社会的活動の情報源となるものである（Rossi et al. 2004: 29）。</p>

<h4 id="問題意識">問題意識</h4>
<p>プログラムの改善に役立てる形成的評価と、アカウンタビリティの確保を目的とする総括的評価からなるプログラム評価を活用することで、社会課題解決に資する地域介入実践の効果を評価できるという仮説を立てる。それを検証するために、中国で実施する社会的介入プログラムを研究対象に、ニーズ評価やセオリー評価、プロセス評価、アウトカム評価、インパクト評価、効率性評価などのプログラム評価法を用いることで地域介入実践の効果を検討する。</p>

<h4 id="研究意義">研究意義</h4>
<p>本研究の意義としては、プログラム評価の視点から社会課題解決に資する地域介入を具現化した社会的介入プログラムの介入効果を評価することにより、地域介入実践の持続可能な発展や地域福祉の増進に寄与することが考えられる。</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="小山セミナー" /><category term="発表" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[研究背景 中国における社会課題解決に資する地域介入実践研究は、2010年代に入り徐々に活発となっている。そのうち、大半はアメリカのコミュニティ・オーガニゼーション（CO）研究者であるジャック・ロスマンが提唱されたコミュニティ・インターベンション理論を活用したうえで、コミュニティに存在するボランティア参加、待機児童、住宅問題、貧困、ホームレス、環境保全、社会的孤立などさまざまな社会課題を解決するために社会的介入プログラムという形式で行われている。しかしながら、社会課題に応じる地域介入実践の効果を評価する必要性が論じられているが、どのような方法で評価するのが妥当なのか、いわゆる評価方法論が未だに確立されていない状況にある。そのため、社会的介入プログラムの効果をシステマティックに検討できるプログラム評価の活用を視野に入れている。]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">主観的健康感がボランティア活動参加に及ぼす影響に対する友人関係の調整効果</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/%E8%AA%BF%E6%95%B4%E5%8A%B9%E6%9E%9C/2023/04/14/%E5%81%A5%E5%BA%B7%E3%81%8C%E3%83%9C%E3%83%A9%E3%83%B3%E3%83%86%E3%82%A3%E3%82%A2%E5%8F%82%E5%8A%A0%E3%81%AB%E5%8F%8A%E3%81%BC%E3%81%99%E5%BD%B1%E9%9F%BF-%E5%8F%8B%E4%BA%BA%E9%96%A2%E4%BF%82%E3%81%AE%E8%AA%BF%E6%95%B4%E5%8A%B9%E6%9E%9C.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="主観的健康感がボランティア活動参加に及ぼす影響に対する友人関係の調整効果" /><published>2023-04-14T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2023-04-14T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/%E8%AA%BF%E6%95%B4%E5%8A%B9%E6%9E%9C/2023/04/14/%E5%81%A5%E5%BA%B7%E3%81%8C%E3%83%9C%E3%83%A9%E3%83%B3%E3%83%86%E3%82%A3%E3%82%A2%E5%8F%82%E5%8A%A0%E3%81%AB%E5%8F%8A%E3%81%BC%E3%81%99%E5%BD%B1%E9%9F%BF%20%E5%8F%8B%E4%BA%BA%E9%96%A2%E4%BF%82%E3%81%AE%E8%AA%BF%E6%95%B4%E5%8A%B9%E6%9E%9C</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/%E8%AA%BF%E6%95%B4%E5%8A%B9%E6%9E%9C/2023/04/14/%E5%81%A5%E5%BA%B7%E3%81%8C%E3%83%9C%E3%83%A9%E3%83%B3%E3%83%86%E3%82%A3%E3%82%A2%E5%8F%82%E5%8A%A0%E3%81%AB%E5%8F%8A%E3%81%BC%E3%81%99%E5%BD%B1%E9%9F%BF-%E5%8F%8B%E4%BA%BA%E9%96%A2%E4%BF%82%E3%81%AE%E8%AA%BF%E6%95%B4%E5%8A%B9%E6%9E%9C.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="ロジットモデルによる結果推定">ロジット・モデルによる結果推定</h1>

<p><img src="/images/230414.png" alt="image description" width="800" height="600" /></p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>变量</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">B</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">標準偏差</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">有意差</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">EXP（B）</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">上限</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">下限</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>主観的健康感ref:不良</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.172</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.070</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.014</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.188</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.036</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.361</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>友人関係</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">-.044</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.025</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.079</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.957</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.912</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.005</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>交差項</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.045</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.020</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.024</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.046</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.006</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.087</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>年齢</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">-.067</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.026</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.009</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.935</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.889</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.983</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>收入</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.242</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.026</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.000</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.274</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.210</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.340</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>性别ref:男</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.064</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.050</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.198</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.066</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.967</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.176</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>学歴ref:中学校未満</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.396</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.054</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.000</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.485</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.336</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.651</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>民族ref:汉民族</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.349</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.155</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.000</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">3.855</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">2.845</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">5.224</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>宗教ref:無宗教</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">-.098</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.100</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.327</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.103</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.907</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1.343</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>定数</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">-.685</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.103</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.000</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">.504</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"> </td>
      <td style="text-align: center"> </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h1 id="調整効果図">調整効果図</h1>

<p><img src="/images/230308.png" alt="image description" width="800" height="600" /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="調整効果" /><category term="研究" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ロジット・モデルによる結果推定]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">プログラム評価における媒介効果</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/%E3%83%97%E3%83%AD%E3%82%B0%E3%83%A9%E3%83%A0%E8%A9%95%E4%BE%A1/2023/04/13/%E5%AA%92%E4%BB%8B%E5%8A%B9%E6%9E%9C.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="プログラム評価における媒介効果" /><published>2023-04-13T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2023-04-13T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/%E3%83%97%E3%83%AD%E3%82%B0%E3%83%A9%E3%83%A0%E8%A9%95%E4%BE%A1/2023/04/13/%E5%AA%92%E4%BB%8B%E5%8A%B9%E6%9E%9C</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/%E3%83%97%E3%83%AD%E3%82%B0%E3%83%A9%E3%83%A0%E8%A9%95%E4%BE%A1/2023/04/13/%E5%AA%92%E4%BB%8B%E5%8A%B9%E6%9E%9C.html"><![CDATA[<script type="module"> import mermaid from 'https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/mermaid@10.0.2/+esm'; mermaid.initialize({ startOnLoad: true }); </script>

<h1 id="媒介効果とは何か直接的効果">媒介効果とは何か（直接的効果）</h1>
<p>媒介効果（mediation effect）とは、原因と結果の間にあって双方の関係を仲介する要因の効果を意味する。多くの介入では、プログラム自体を原因とし、プログラム参加者へのアウトカム、つまり「結果」への直接的な効果が測定される。しかし、このような因果関係図式に基づいたアウトカムの測定では、プログラムの何が、どのような経路を経てアウトカムに影響を及ぼしたか、という過程は明らかにはならない。つまり、プログラムの過程をブラックボックス化させてしまい、プログラムの介入の効果があったかどうか、効果の大きさはどの程度であったか、という直接的な因果関係のみが考察される。</p>

<div class="mermaid">
flowchart LR
    プログラム原因--&gt;|直接的効果|アウトカム結果
</div>

<h1 id="媒介効果とは何か媒介効果">媒介効果とは何か（媒介効果）</h1>

<p>一方、プログラム自体が原因であることに変わりはないが、プログラムからアウトカムへの影響（c係数）は、媒介要因を通じて起こると想定している。つまり、アウトカムは原因からの影響（a係数）のほか、媒介要因からの影響（b係数）も受けることにある。</p>

<div class="mermaid">
flowchart LR
    プログラム原因--&gt;|a|媒介要因
    媒介要因--&gt;|b|アウトカム結果
    プログラム原因--&gt;|c|アウトカム結果
</div>

<h1 id="媒介効果とは何か媒介効果の影響">媒介効果とは何か（媒介効果の影響）</h1>
<p>媒介効果の影響が統計学的に同定されるためには以下の条件を満たす必要がある。</p>
<ol>
  <li>プログラムが媒介要因に影響を及ぼし（パス係数aが統計的に有意）</li>
  <li>媒介要因がプログラムのアウトカムに影響を及ぼし（パス係数bが統計的に有意）</li>
  <li>プログラムと媒介要因との関係（パス係数a）及び媒介要因とアウトカムとの関係（バス係数b)が統計的にコントロールされることにより、もともとのプログラムとアウトカムの直接的な関係が軽減されるあるいは消滅する（パス係数cが有意から有意でなくなる）
（Baron &amp; Kenny, 1986）</li>
</ol>

<h1 id="完全媒介">完全媒介</h1>
<p>媒介分析において、完全媒介とは、原因と結果の間にある媒介変数が、原因と結果の関係に完全に関与することを指します。つまり、原因が結果に与える影響は、その媒介変数を通じて完全に説明できるということです。</p>

<div class="mermaid">
flowchart LR
    X--&gt;|a|M
    M--&gt;|b|Y
    X-.-&gt;|c|Y
</div>

<h1 id="部分媒介">部分媒介</h1>
<p>不完全媒介とは、媒介変数が原因と結果の間の関係に一部しか関与していない場合を指します。つまり、媒介変数が原因と結果の関係を部分的に説明することができるが、原因と結果の関係の一部は、媒介変数とは独立して存在するということです。A-.-&gt;B</p>

<div class="mermaid">
flowchart LR
    X--&gt;|a|M
    M--&gt;|b|Y
    X--&gt;|c|Y
</div>

<h1 id="媒介効果測定の重要性">媒介効果測定の重要性</h1>
<p>プログラム評価において、媒介効果を測定する理由には、以下の3つがある。</p>
<ol>
  <li>プログラムがどういう過程を経て実際に変化（効果）をもたらしているかがチェックできる。</li>
  <li>プログラムのどこをどのように強化・改善すべきかを知ることができる。</li>
  <li>もしプログラムが効果をもたらしていなかった場合には媒介要因の影響が後から出現するかあるいは媒介要因はアウトカムに関係のないものであったかを判断できる。
（MacKinnon &amp; Dwyer, 1993)</li>
</ol>

<h1 id="例としてのエイズ感染予防プログラム">例としてのエイズ感染予防プログラム</h1>
<ol>
  <li>プログラム（キャンペーン）により、エイズを予防する知識が増せば、エイズウイルスへの感染が減ることが予想される。つまり、プログラム（原因）は、プログラムへの参加者のエイズに関する知識（媒介要因）を向上させ、その結果、エイズウイルスへの感染（結果）を防ぐことにつながると仮定ができる。このように、プログラム介入によってターゲットとなる媒介要因に変化が起こったかどうか、というのを確認するのである。</li>
</ol>
<div class="mermaid">
flowchart LR
    プログラム--&gt;|a|知識の向上
    知識の向上--&gt;|b|感染の予防
    プログラム--&gt;|c|感染の予防
</div>

<ol>
  <li>もしこのエイズ感染予防プログラムの効果が思うように上がっていない場合には、キャンペーンの対象者に今まで以上にエイズの知識の啓蒙・伝達を行い、感染の防止に努めることが考えられる。ここでは、媒介要因と仮定される対象者の知識向上を促すプログラムを強化し、感染を防ぐようにできる。</li>
  <li>プログラム実際には感染予防に効果をもたらしていない場合には、③の可能性がうかがえる。つまり、エイズ感染予防の知識向上は、エイズ感染の低減につながるまでにプログラムの実施期間以上の時間を要する。または関係がないという可能性である。例えば、感染を低減するためには、知識ではなく、行動的な側面に焦点を当てたものが必要だったのかもしれない。つまり、プログラムの仮説上の設定ミスあるいは理論上の問題。</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="プログラム評価" /><category term="媒介効果" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">プログラム評価における調整効果</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/%E3%83%97%E3%83%AD%E3%82%B0%E3%83%A9%E3%83%A0%E8%A9%95%E4%BE%A1/2023/04/13/%E8%AA%BF%E6%95%B4%E5%8A%B9%E6%9E%9C.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="プログラム評価における調整効果" /><published>2023-04-13T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2023-04-13T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/%E3%83%97%E3%83%AD%E3%82%B0%E3%83%A9%E3%83%A0%E8%A9%95%E4%BE%A1/2023/04/13/%E8%AA%BF%E6%95%B4%E5%8A%B9%E6%9E%9C</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/%E3%83%97%E3%83%AD%E3%82%B0%E3%83%A9%E3%83%A0%E8%A9%95%E4%BE%A1/2023/04/13/%E8%AA%BF%E6%95%B4%E5%8A%B9%E6%9E%9C.html"><![CDATA[<script type="module"> import mermaid from 'https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/mermaid@10.0.2/+esm'; mermaid.initialize({ startOnLoad: true }); </script>

<h1 id="調整効果">調整効果</h1>
<p>媒介要因は、プログラムと結果の因果連鎖（causal link）の間に位置する要因を意味する。一方、調整要因は、プログラムとの交互作用（interaction）によって結果に影響を及ぼす要因を指す。例えば、男性と女性によってプログラムの効果が違う場合。ここでは、プログラム（原因）とアウト
カム（結果）との関係が、性別という要因によって調整されている。つまり、男性（a係数）と女性（b係数）の値が性別によって異なる場合、「性別」が調整要因となる。</p>

<h1 id="性别">性别</h1>
<p>男性</p>
<div class="mermaid">
flowchart LR
    プログラム原因--&gt;|a|アウトカム結果
</div>

<p>女性</p>
<div class="mermaid">
flowchart LR
    プログラム原因--&gt;|b|アウトカム結果
</div>

<h1 id="調整効果の査定">調整効果の査定</h1>
<p>一般に、調整要因（変数）のアウトカムは、プログラムと調整要因の交互作用（c係数）の統計的有意性と効果量によって査定される（Baron &amp; Kenny, 1986）。</p>
<div class="mermaid">
flowchart LR
    プログラム原因--&gt;|a|アウトカム結果
    調整要因--&gt;|b|アウトカム結果
    プログラムと調整要因の交互作用--&gt;|c|アウトカム結果
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="プログラム評価" /><category term="調整効果" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>